Guide to the William W. Akers Chemical Engineering papers and Rice University Vice President for Administration records, 1960-1994 UA 154
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
William W. Akers Chemical Engineering papers and Rice University Vice President for Administration records
1960-1994
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Akers, William W.
UA 154
4 Linear Feet (8 boxes)
The bulk of these records relate to Akers' administrative roles at Rice University, particularly as Vice President for Administration. Correspondence, memos, articles, newsclippings reflect his interests both as university administrator and as professor in the Department of Chemical Engineering.
Biographical / Historical
William W. Akers, Professor Emeritus of Chemical Engineering at Rice University, earned his bachelors degree from Texas Tech University (1943) and his doctorate from the University of Michigan (1950). Professor Akers rose to prominence in the 1960's when he directed research in coordination with the Baylor College of Medicine that produced the first artificial heart. He chaired the chemical engineering department from 1955 to 1965. Since 1973 he has served Rice administratively as development director, vice president for external affairs, and as vice president for administration, while continuing to teach courses in separations processes and process design. He has represented the university in a wide variety of external relationships and is the author or coauthor of more than forty technical publications.
Akers died Nov. 5, 2017 at age 94. [https://news.rice.edu/2017/11/06/bioengineering-pioneer-longtime-professor-william-akers-dies/]
Scope and Contents
The bulk of these records relate to Akers' administrative roles at Rice University, particularly as Vice President for Administration. Correspondence, memos, articles, newsclippings reflect his interests both as university administrator and as professor in the Department of Chemical Engineering. Materials related to the U.S. Civil War and owned by Akers are also present.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Acquisition Information
This material was transferred in June 2007.
Index Terms
Subjects
Soldiers; Universities and colleges
Document Types
daguerreotypes; military uniforms; photographs; corrrespondence
Places
United States
Subjects (Persons)
Gracie, Archibald
- Series I: Bioengineering articles and reports, 1960-1994, 107094
  - AIChE (1992), 107103 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Artificial Heart Program Final Report (1966), 107102 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chemical Engineering (1989), 107101 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Crimes and Punishment Article" (1980s), 107100 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Engineering Data Book (1972), 107099 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Miscellaneous Articles/Papers (1960), 107098 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Plant Pamphlets (1980s), 107097 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Process Design Projects at Penn: 100 Problem Statements" (1994), 107096 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Vista Chemical Scholarship Program (1989), 107095 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
- Series II: Rice University Vice President for Administration, Reader Files, 1980-1986, 127747
  - 1980-1984, 127748 (Box 2-4)
  - 1984-1986, 127749 (Box 4-6)
- Series III: Rice University administrative subject files, 1974-1992, 127890
  - Energy Conservation Study for Rice University (1974), 127892 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Energy (1985-1988), 127893 (Box 6, Folder 2-4)
  - Rice University Fund Council Fall Meeting (1992), 127894 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Graphs (1987), 127895 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Rice University Master Plan for Growth (1983), 127896 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Cesar Pelli Brochure (1985), 127897 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Physical Plant (1986), 127898 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Plant (1988), 127903 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
  - Plant/HLP (1988), 127899 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Physical Plant/HLP (1989), 127900 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Shepherd School of Music (1987), 127901 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - A Music Building for the Shepherd School of Music (1987), 127902 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Series IV: Personal ephemera, 1987-1994 and undated, 127904
  - Space Survey (1987), 127905 (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
  - Eyeglasses (in case), 127906 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Nameplate ("W.W. Akers"), 127907 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Resume/Personal (1994), 127908 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Stationery/Envelopes/Business cards, 127909 (Box 8, Folder 6)